Meier mss., 1927-2010
Indiana University Digital Library Program
- Honors and awards, 1980-2009, undated (Box 13)
  - MacArthur Fellowship, 1985-1988, undated (Box 13)
    - Articles on Meier winning the award, 1987-1988, undated, (1 folder)
      - Teltsch, Kathleen. (1987, Jun. 16). MacArthur Awards of $150,000 to $375,000 Go to 'Outstandingly Talented' 32. New York Times (p. B8)., 6 copies
      - Saari, Jon. (1987, Jun. 17). Two MacArthur Award Winners Associated with Antioch; Brings Total to Four. Antioch News.
      - Sleeper, Jim. (1987, Jun. 29). She Doesn't Like Teaching by the Book. New York Newsday., 2 copies
      - Sleeper, Jim. (1987, Jun. 29). She Doesn't Like Teaching by the Book. New York Newsday., 2 copies (Box 3)
      - Scharrer, Gary. (1987, Aug. 6). Interest in New Fortunes is Academic: Grant Winners Pay Investments No Mind. USA Today. (Box 13)
      - Foster, Catherine. (1987, Oct. 30.) Prestige Prize for a Principal: MacArthur Grant Honors Deborah Meier--and her Innovative School. Christian Science Monitor., 3 copies
      - Foster, Catherine. (1987, Oct. 30.) Prestige Prize for a Principal: MacArthur Grant Honors Deborah Meier--and her Innovative School. Christian Science Monitor., 3 copies (Box 3)
      - (1987, Oct.) MacArthur Award's First School Teacher. The American Teacher., 4 copies (Box 13)
      - (1987, Oct.) MacArthur Award's First School Teacher. The American Teacher., 4 copies (Box 3)
      - Teltsch, Kathleen. Howe, 31 Others Get 'Genius Grants.' New York Times, 1987 (Box 13)
      - Pierson, Ransdell. Harlem Teacher Receives 300G MacArthur Gift. New York Post, 1987
      - (1988, Feb. 17). 'Genius' in a Ghetto School. St. Louis Post-Dispatch, 2 copies (Box 3)
      - In Harlem, Education is Praised, undated, Second page only (Box 13)
    - Letters of congratulation, 1987, undated, (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - General, 1980-2009 (Box 14)
    - Fund for the City of New York Public Service Award, 1980-2008, undated, (2 folders)
      Includes nomination essay (2 copies), plaque, article Six Civil Service Employees Honored, and program from 2008 listing all the previous winners
      (Plaque located at the end of the honors and awards series)
      See also: MacArthur Fellowship; binder of recommendations, resumes, articles, etc., includes 1 copy of article
    - University of Chicago Alumni Award, 1988
      Includes correspondence and program
    - Building Brick Award, 1988, Jan. 7
    - Paul DuBrul Award, 1993, June 24
      Includes event program, pamphlet, and speech by Ruth Jordan
    - Windstar Award Nomination, 1993
      Includes nomination materials and Windstar pamphlet
    - John Dewey Society Award, 1994, Dec. 5
      Includes presentation speech and note from Nel Noddings and flyer
    - New York Academy of Public Education Award, 1995, May 9
      Includes 3 programs and 2 newsletters
    - Debs-Thomas-Harrington Award, 1996, May 3
      Includes program and photocopy
      See also: The Power of Public Education article by Meier
    - Dinner with Vice President Al Gore and Family Re-Union Conference, 1997
      Includes letter from Al Gore, seating cards, conference and dinner program, and autographed photograph of Al Gore and Tipper Gore
    - Michael Harrington Lifetime Achievement Award, 1998, June 4, (2 folders)
      Includes invitation, program, congratulations letters from Senator Edward M. Kennedy and Representative John F. Tierney, article, and plaque
    - Horace Mann Award, 2001, July 27
      Includes award and programs
    - John W. Porter Distinguished Chair in Urban Education, 2008, Feb. 7 (Box 1)
      Includes certificate
    - Rabbi Marshall T. Meyer Risk-Taker Award, 2008, Nov. 20 (Box 14)
      Includes invitation, program, and presentation speech
    - Fairtest Honors Deborah W. Meier, 2009, June 4
      Includes 2 programs
  - Honorary degrees, 1988-1998 (Box 14)
    - Clark University, 1988, May 15
      Includes commencement program
    - Columbia University, 1988, Nov. 29
      Includes convocation program
    - Brown University, 1989 (Box 14)
      Includes article and commencement program
    - Brown University, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Yale University, 1993 (Box 14)
      Includes commencement program, article
    - Yale University, 1993 (Box 1)
      Includes diploma
    - Harvard University, 1993 (Box 14)
      Includes invitation, 2 dinner programs, and commencement program
      See also: 1993 Harvard Commencement Morning Exercises, VHS
    - New School for Social Research, 1995, June-July (Box 3)
      Includes article
    - Dartmouth College, 1996, June 9
      Includes commencement program and article
    - Dartmouth College, 1996, June 9 (Box 14)
    - Bard College, 1997, May 24
      Includes program, presentation speech, and diploma
    - Hebrew Union College, 1997, June 4
      Includes correspondence, program pages, and photograph
    - University at Albany, 1998, May 17
      Includes correspondence and 2 commencement programs
    - State University of New York, 1998, May 17
    - Lesley College, 1998, May 26
      Includes 2 commencement programs
      See also: Lesley College commencement speech
    - Lesley College, 1998, May 26 (Box 1)
    - University of Massachusetts, Lowell, 1998, June 7 (Box 14)
      Includes commencement program, article, and diploma
  - Membership and participation acknowledgements, 1990-2005, undated (Box 14)
    - PDC Principal Partner plaque, 1990-1991
    - National Academy of Education membership certificate, 1993, Oct. 28
    - Syracuse City School District Leadership Institute Keynote Speaker plaque, 1995, July 6
    - Acknowledgement from the Boston Public Schools and the Center for Leadership Development for serving as a mentor for the Preparation for Principalship Program, 1999, Feb.-Apr.
    - Thank-you plaque from the Small School of the Arts at South Shore High School, 2002, Oct. 23
    - Pi Lambda Theta membership and conference participation certificates, 2005, July
    - Welcome certificate from Jerry Brown, mayor of Oakland, California, undated
- Politics, 1950-1993, undated (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1993, undated (Box 14)
    - General, 1950-1981, undated
      Abrams, Sheldon (Shelley), 1955-1956
      Ahearn, Ray, 1957
      Arden, Pat, 1957
      Blum, Eugene, 1968
      Bolitzer, Bernie, 1964
      Bone, Bob, ca. 1957
      Bottone, Phyllis, 1962
      Bottone, Sam, 1957
      Bram, Harold and Paula, 1957
      Brockway, Fenner, M.P., House of Commons, 1954
      Burnett, James, 1957
      Clark, Jack, 1981
      Coleman, H. D., 1952
      Dahlgren, Carl E., 1967
      Denitch, Bogdan, 1957, 1962-1963
      Dombrow, Max, 1978
      Draper, Hal, 1956
      Elkin, Betty, 1963
      Gallagher, Jim, 1958
      Gates, Albert, national secretary of the Independent Socialist League, 1951, 1956-1957
      Harrington, Michael (Mike), 1956-1957, 1963
      Haskell, Gordon (Gordo), 1957
      Horowitz, Rachelle, 1962, 1964
      Howe, Irving, 1969
      Landy, Sy, 1957-1958
      Lowe, Arthur, 1957
      Martin, Max, national secretary of the YSL, 1954-1957, 1962
      MacKenzie, George R., 1957
      Meier, Deborah, 1953, 1956-1958, 1969
      Rawick, George, 1951-1952, 1954, 1956-1958, 1962
      Sagen, N., 1954
      Schapiro, Meyer, chairman of the Committee for an Independent Socialist Magazine, 1953
      Shute, Mike, 1957
      Stern, Will, 1969
      Thomas, Don, 1957-1958
      Tussing, Arlon, YSL member, 1955-1957
      University of Chicago, 1954
      Walker, Charles, 1957
      Waller, Paul, 1957
      Witthoft, Bill, business manager of Anvil and Student Partisan, 1950-1951
      Wohlforth, Tim, 1957-ca. 1958
      - 1950-1952
      - 1953-1954
      - 1955-1956, Apr.
      - 1955-1956, Apr. (Box 3)
      - 1956, May-Dec.
      - 1956, May-Dec. (Box 14)
      - 1957, Jan.-Mar. (Box 15)
      - 1957, Apr.-June
      - 1957, July-Dec.
      - ca. 1957
      - 1958
      - ca. 1957-1958
      - 1962-1981
      - ca. 1960s
    - Irving Howe, 1952-1981
    - Don Rose, 1993, undated
  - Writings by Meier, 1954-1983, undated (Box 15)
    Arranged alphabetically
    - ( 1978, Oct.). Looking Backward: DSOC Marks Fifth Year. Newsletter of the Democratic Left, volume 6, number 8 (pp. 1, 6-7), 1978, 2 printed
    - The Middle East is not the O.K. Corral. In These Times. Undated, 1 printed
    - ( 1983, March). Nagging Questions. Democratic Left (pp. 9-11). 1983, 4 printed
    - ( 1954, May 31). The New Fellow Travelers: Apologists for Chiang's Concentration Camps. Young Socialist Challenge, volume 6. 1954, 1 printed (Box 3)
    - ( 1983, Jan.). Report Number 5. In Mike Conroy & Glenn Scott (Eds.), D.S.A. Reports on Nicaragua (pp. 17-21). 1983, 1 printed (Box 15)
    - re: Metropolitan CORE and the CORE Summer Project. Undated, 1 draft, includes letter from Deborah Meir
    - With Rafael PiRoman. ( 1983, Apr. 22). The Revolution and Democracy. Commonweal, (pp. 234-239). 1983, 1 printed
    - ( 1982, Summer). Socialism and the Family. Feminist Perspectives on the Family, volume 10 (pp. 21-23). 1982, 2 printed
    - With Michael Harrington. Socialist Values and Everyday Life. Theory, Life, and Politics. Undated, 1 printed
    - ( 1954, Oct. 18). Triumph of 'Crackpot Realism': A Liberal Comes Out for Franco. Young Socialist Challenge (p. 3). 1954, 1 printed (Box 3)
    - Untitled. Undated, 1 draft (Box 15)
  - Speeches and notes by Meier, 1950s, undated (Box 15)
    - DSA speech, undated
    - DSOC and general, 1950s, undated
      - 'Americanoid' and 'Stalinoid' stand in parallel relationship to each other..., 1950s, Notecards
      - DSOC too - this morning - Trapped. Sense of humor about taking this moment too seriously..., undated
      - When DSOC was founded in 1973, we hoped someday to be strong enough to help foster the kind of political gathering which we have with us today..., undated
      - Issue: pervasiveness of perceived reality, how we perceive, understand reality (emporer's clothes)..., undated
      - Today we've seen and heard and shared a picture of what the corporate powers of America have done to our dreams..., undated
      - There are some advantages in having come of age in 1950..., undated
    - Civil rights, race relations, integration, undated
      - What I wish to try to do this afternoon may be impossible. But my hope was that Mr Fiers would be able to outline for you both the futility of 'running'..., undated
      - We raised in the last issue two problems which recent evets would indicate are going to cause us increasing trouble: (1) the possible differences between the demands of the Negro middle class leadership..., undated
      - Problem of self-understanding..., undated
      - What are the social problems this framework poses us with..., undated
      - An Historical Perspective on the Black Power Epoch, undated
      - Notes, undated
      - I. Election over: politics. Not just the same, but different: Sixties transforming..., undated
      - What must we understand about ourselves, our attitudes, & prejudices in order to adapt to inter-racial experience..., undated, Notecards
    - China, undated
      - It was hard for me, imbued as I am with somewhat stubbornly entrenched theories about individualism & freedom, to comprehend what is happening in China..., undated, Notecards
      - China imp: obvious, basic alternatives in world: question of pol toward socialist value system..., undated
  - Activities, 1953-1968, undated (Box 15)
    - Chicago Young People's Socialist League (YPSL) and University of Chicago Politics Club Binder, 1959, undated
      Includes meeting announcements, circulars, forms, flyers, and articles
    - Documents related to various socialist groups, 1953-1968, undated
      Includes constitution, bulletins, newsletters, reports, and statements
    - Miscellaneous documents and correspondence related to socialism and the NAACP, 1955-1959, undated
  - FBI file, 1955-1988 (Box 15)
    - FBI file request correspondence, 1987-1988
    - FBI file on Meier, 1955-1963
- Recordings and multimedia, 1970-2008, undated (Box 17)
  - Meier speeches, interviews, and panel discussions, 1993-2008
    - Audio, 1993-2004, undated
      - Fresh Air, WNYC (New York Public Radio), interview with Meier, 1993, Aug. 26, Cassette tape, 30:00 (second side blank)
      - Helen, Ted, Ada-, Deb, 1995, Aug. 8, Cassette tape, 60:00
        Recording of a conversation about education; includes Meier
      - AERA 1996 Annual Meeting, Enriching Our Understanding of Schools as Democratic Communities; speech by Meier, 1996, April 8-12, Cassette tape, 85:00
        Also includes a speech titled Reimagining America and the Creation of Democratic Schools
      - Coalition of Essential Schools Fall Forum 1997, Learning to Exercise Good Judgement vs. Learning to Get One Right Answer, San Francisco, California; speech by Meier followed by a question-and-answer session, 1997, Nov. 5-9, 2 cassette tapes, 60:00 and 53:00
        Meier included on both tapes
      - A Conversation with… Deborah Meier, The Merrow Report, ASCD (Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development), 1997, Cassette tape, 55:00
        Interview with Meier
      - An interview with Meier on The Connection, 90.9 WBUR (Boston's NPR News station), 1999, Feb. 4, 2 cassette tapes (2 copies of the interview); 52:00 and 55:00
      - High Stakes Testing: What are the Effects? conference, Teachers College, Columbia University, 2000, Mar. 31
        - Opening panel, 2000, Mar. 31, Cassette tape, 90:00
          The panelists include Judith Rizzo (deputy chancellor of New York City schools); Richard Rothstein (researcher with the Economic Policy Institute, education columnist with the New York Times); Theresa Fay-Bustillos (attorney with MALDEF (Mexican-American Legal Defense and Education Fund); Vito Perrone (with the Teaching and Learning Program at Harvard); Monty Neill (director of the National Center for Fair and Open Testing); Michelle Fine (researcher with City University of New York); and Olivia Lynch (principal of the School for Academic and Athletic Excellence in New York City). The moderator is Thomas Sobol (Professor at Columbia Teachers College)
        - Speech by Paul Wellstone, U.S. Senator from Minnesota, 2000, Mar. 31, Cassette tape, 41:00 (side B blank)
        - Speech by Deborah Meier, 2000, Mar. 31, Cassette tape, 29:00 (side B blank)
      - Progressive Ed: Deb, Wolf, etc., recorded discussion, 2003, Nov. 11, Cassette tape, 60:00 (begins on side B)
        Educators at Mission Hill School discussing their definition of progressive education; includes a few comments from Meier
      - Cambridge Forum Radio, Many Children Left Behind: Deborah Meier, Monty Neill & Ted Sizer, 2004, Oct. 27, CD, 58:05
        Discussion of the book Many Children Left Behind by Meier, Monty Neill and Theodore R. Sizer with host Tony Wagner
      - Deborah Meier Interview Edited, recording of Meier speaking, undated, CD, 7:43
    - Video and digital photographs, 1990-2008, undated
      - Education for 21st Century Citizenship: A Convergence of Agendas, Cambridge College; panel with Meier and ten other panelists, 1990, Dec. 12, VHS, 45:00 (Box 16)
      - 9th annual Socialist Scholars Conference opening session, THI Plenary: The Crisis in Education, 1991, Apr. 5, VHS, 88:35
        Includes speeches by Meier, Cornel West, Stanley Aronowitz, and Joseph Murphy
      - 342nd Harvard Commencement Morning Exercises, including a speech by Meier, 1993, June 10, VHS, 126:00
        See also: Harvard University Honorary Degree
      - Women's American ORT (Organization for Rehabilitation through Training) installation dinner at Miami Beach, presentation of the Beverly Minkoff Education Award to Meier and her acceptance speech, 1993, Oct. 17,7:30 P.M. - 11:10 P.M., VHS, 124:47
        See also: Women's American ORT convention speech
      - Syracuse City School District Leadership Institute, keynote speech by Meier, 1995, July 6, VHS, 40:00
      - Educational Reform, Women to Women, CUNY-TV (City University of New York TV), 1995, July 18, VHS, 31:30
        Discussion between host Frances Degen Horowitz and guests Carol Gresser and Meier
      - Conversation Pieces: An Afternoon with Ted Sizer, Deborah Meier, and Dennis Littky, 1995, VHS, 81:44
        A discussion between the three participants in response to three clips from the documentaries and films High School II, A Private Universe, and A Town Torn Apart
      - Afternoon Edition Segment with host Denise Richardson, News Talk Television, 1996, Feb. 16, VHS, 177:57
        Includes a segment titled Teachers Disciplining Students with Meier and Monica Simmons responding to callers. Also includes segments on Bob Dole and Pat Buchanan, gun ads, testing athletes for AIDS, and underage drinking.
      - Education Under Fire. #1: Collaborative Schools: Sharing the Power, Phi Delta Kappa, interview with Meier, 1996, VHS, 28:55
      - Robert Stevenson Lecture by Meier titled New Approaches that Will Enhance Democracy and Equity in Public Education at the ATE (Association of Teacher Educators) annual meeting, 1997, Feb., VHS, 73:00
        Includes several other speeches and the presentation of the National Student Teacher/Intern of the Year award
      - Accountability in a Restructuring System, the Panasonic Foundation Partnership Conference IX, speech by Meier titled Accountability: The View from the School, 1997, Mar. 1-3, VHS, 107:30
      - Coalition of Essential Schools Fall Forum, opening and closing sessions, 1998, Nov., VHS, 94:41
        Opening session includes speeches by Amy Gerstein and Theodore R. Sizer; closing session includes a speech by Meier
      - Coalition of Essential Schools Fall Forum: Essential Teaching and Learning, opening and closing sessions, 2000, VHS, 90:00
        Opening session includes speeches by Theodore R. Sizer and Cornel West; closing session includes speech by Meier
      - Eye on Education Forum, Greater Boston Forum, WGBH, 2000, Nov. 16, VHS, 92:00
        Two panel discussions. The first panel includes panelists Meier, Jane Swift (Massachusetts Lt. Governor), Thomas Payzant (Superintendent Boston Public Schools), Felix Arroyo (co-chairman of POWER), Abigail Thernstrom (member of the Massachusetts Board of Education), and Cecil Hunt (professor Suffolk University Law School) with host Emily Rooney
      - 16th Cynthia Longfellow lecture at the Child Development Institute at Sarah Lawrence College by Meier titled In Schools We Trust: What Kind of Schooling Nourishes Democracy?, 2002, Nov. 4, VHS, 92:49
      - Lawrence Public Schools District Instructional Conference, 2003, Jan. 21
        - Speech by Meier titled In Schools We Trust, 2003, Jan. 21, VHS, 98:00
        - Workshop, question and answer session with Meier, and panel discussion, 2003, Jan. 21, VHS, 117:30
      - Stanford University, 2003, Mar. 7
        - Speech by Meier, 2003, Mar. 7, VHS, 64:06
        - Interview with Meier, 2003, Mar. 7, VHS, 52:00
      - Accountability in Support of Schools, Teachers and Children: A Symposium at Teachers College, Columbia University, 2005, Apr. 20, DVD, 26:48 (Box 17)
        Includes presenters Douglas Christensen, Peter McWalters, and James Lytle; respondents Gerry House and Meier; and moderator Charles Fowler
      - Coalition of Essential Schools convention in Chicago; speeches by Meier and Linda Darling-Hammond, 2006, Nov. 4, DVD, 27:31
      - Bildungspreis, Padagogische hochschule zurich, 2007
        - Speech by Meier accepting an award, 2007, CD, Quicktime movie 22:33
        - Photographs, 2007, DVD, 146 photographs in three folders labeled Bühl, Gründungstag, and Modul BE 340
      - John W. Porter Distinguished Chair in Urban Education speech by Meier titled Educating for what? The Struggle for Democracy in Education at Eastern Michigan University, 2008, Feb. 7, 2 DVDs, 52:21 and 35:35
      - AERO (Alternative Education Resource Organization) Conference, 2008
        - Play and Democracy workshop led by Meier, 2008, DVD, 54:47
        - Keynote speech by Meier, 2008, DVD, 94:45
      - National-Louis University Call to Action, The Forum for Education and Democracy, panel discussion with George Wood, Meier, and Bill Ayers followed by a break-out session, undated, 2 DVDs, 18:08 and 18:08 (2 copies of the same program labeled The Forum for Education and Democracy for Deborah Meier and No Child Left Behind Conference at National-Louis University)
      - Great Neck Public Schools Superintendent's Conference Day keynote address by Meier titled Raising Expectations of Student Achievement, undated, VHS, 64:00 (Box 16)
        See also: Great Neck Public Schools Superintendent's Conference Day: Raising Expectations of Student Achievement; conference program
  - Programs on education, 1990-2005, undated
    - Why Do These Kids Love School? 1990, VHS, 60:00
      Documentary produced by Dorothy Fadiman and KTEH-TV San Jose featuring nine successful schools, including CPE II,
    - Common Miracles: The New American Revolution in Learning, ABC News Special, 1993, Jan. 23, VHS, 50:00
    - Effective School Restructuring: Putting Together the Pieces, second videoconference for the National Forum for Effective School Restructuring, New York State Education Department Public Broadcasting Program; panel discussion with Dr. Linda Darling Hammond, Doris Culver, and Dr. Adam Urbanski, 1993, Feb. 22, VHS, 96:12
      See also: Inserts and booklets; note from Peter Hart to Meier
    - School Design, rough cut, 1995, Dec. 22, VHS, 62:00
      Documentary on Fannie Lou Hamer Freedom High School; Meier assists in giving a tour of the school and participates in a group discussion
    - Cambridge College: From the Inside Out, 1995, VHS, 10:14
      Program on teaching and learning at Cambridge College
    - High School that Makes Sense, Annenberg Institute for School Reform and the Coalition of Essential Schools, 1996, Sept. 4, VHS, 33:35
      Documentary on three high schools: Chicago Vocational High School (Chicago, IL), Souhegan High School (Amherst, NH), and University Heights High School (Bronx, NY)
    - The Merrow Report: In Schools We Trust, 1997, Jan. 15, VHS, 57:00
      Program on the history of American schools, includes segments with Meier
      See also: Inserts and booklets; The Merrow Report: In Schools We Trust booklet (contains an interview with Meier)
    - Education's Big Gamble: Charter Schools, The Merrow Report, 1997, Sept., VHS, 57:00
    - Settings for Change, 1997, VHS, 32:10
      Program on testing and how Felton Elementary Schools in Lennox School District, Lennox, CA raised their test scores
    - An interview on CUNY-TV with three organizers of The Fight for America's Future: A Teach-In with the Labor Movement, a conference at Columbia University; an episode of CUNY-TV's The Urban Agenda; A Firing Line Debate on school vouchers with William F. Buckley, Jr. [recording ends before the program concludes]; The Urban Agenda episode repeats; an episode of CUNY-TV's Metroview on the 9th annual CUNY Big Apple job fair; CUNY-TV Jerusalem On Line program; CUNY-TV's The City Club of New York Friday Forum on June 13, 1997 on recycling; and Mystery! episode titled Maigret on the Defensive, 1997, VHS, 360:00
      Conference organizers interviewed: Carrie Kim (UNITE), Jonathan Cutler (CUNY Graduate Center), and Joshua Freeman
      Person interviewed on The Urban Agenda: David Butler, assistant director of MDRC (Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation)
      The Firing Line Debate resolution: Government Should Not Discriminate Against Private Schools; for the resolution: William F. Buckley, Jr., Pete du Pont, Jimmy Mansour, and Brother Bob Smith; against the resolution: William E. Curry, Jr., Ira Glasser, Christopher Edley, Jr., and Bob Chase